Finding Aid for College of Pharmacy (University of Michigan) Publications 1880-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
College of Pharmacy (University of Michigan) publications 1880-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.
Includes bibliographies, pamphlets, bulletins and college catalogs, histories, manuals such as Drugs and Pharmacy, newsletters such as the College of Pharmacy Newsletter, posters, proceedings and programs. Also contains publications from the Pharmacy Advancement Program such as Interactions and InterUMactions, as well as alumni directories and student publications such as Capsules, Equilibrium, The Hash Sheet, Pharmacy Newsletter, and Pharmacy Paper.
97119 Bimu C81 2
2.8 linear feet in 4 boxes
1.2 MB online
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the College of Pharmacy (donor # 3112 ).
College of Pharmacy (University of Michigan) publications are open for research.
The College of Pharmacy dates from the appointment of Douglass Houghton in 1839 as professor of Geology, Mineralogy, and "with the subjects of Chemistry and Pharmacy, till Regents take further order in relation thereto." In 1844, Houghton was joined by his cousin Silas Hamilton Douglass who was charged with assisting in the instruction of chemistry and related sciences. Although it does not appear that Douglass taught any pharmacy courses, it was under his direction in 1860 that the first pharmacy laboratory course was offered by an assistant, Alfred DuBois. Upon DuBois' departure from the university in 1863, the regents appointed two student assistants to cover DuBois' responsibilities, Henry S. Cheever and Albert B. Prescott. Prescott completed his academic degree in 1864, served for a year in the U.S. Army, and returned to the University as an assistant professor of chemistry. In 1868, the regents established "Pharmaceutical Chemistry" as a degree-granting program within the Department of Literature, Science, and Arts. The program expanded again, in 1876 to become the School of Pharmacy with Prescott as dean. (The name was changed to the College of Pharmacy in 1915, in accordance with university policy adopted at that time.)
Under Prescott's leadership the curriculum was set at a year-and-a-half program leading to a pharmaceutical chemistry degree. Recognition of the program by the American Pharmaceutical Association was initially refused in 1871 because the Michigan format emphasized basic sciences instead of the apprenticeship system. By 1885, however, several major universities had copied the Michigan program and accreditation followed as the value of the scientific approach was recognized. A graduate studies program had been added in 1882 and in 1895 a bachelor of sciences degree was initiated to supplement the basic undergraduate program.
Upon the death of Dr. Prescott in 1905, the deanship was assumed by Julius O. Schlotterbeck, who served for twelve years and ushered in an era of expanded student services and activities. Field trips to pharmaceutical firms such as Upjohn Company, and Parke-Davis, and Company became annual activities. Student financial support was provided through the Prescott Memorial Loan Fund beginning in 1906. Two student societies were formed in 1908 to encourage scholarship and social interaction. The Aristolochite Society was formed as a local honors organization for exceptional pharmacy students. In 1922, it became the Alpha chapter of the Rho Chi (RX) Society. The Prescott Club, which was open to all pharmacy students, sponsored lectures and social activities. In 1946 the Prescott Club became the A.B. Prescott Student Chapter, American Pharmaceutical Association.
In 1920, after a three-year period in which the college was led by Alviso B. Stevens (1917-1919) and Henry Kraemer (1919-1920), Edward H. Kraus began a fourteen-year tenure as dean. He initiated the doctoral program in pharmacy and encouraged corporate-sponsored fellowships for graduate students. Kraus gave Professor Frederick F. Blicke responsibility for training graduate students in synthetic organic pharmaceutical chemistry. Blicke became a recognized leader in this field and was mentor to dozens of doctoral candidates.
Howard B. Lewis served as dean of the College of Pharmacy from 1933 to 1947, and steered the school through the difficult years of the Great Depression and World War II. From a low point of only forty four students in February 1933, Lewis was able to increase enrollment to seventy two students in March, 1935. Thereafter, the College of Pharmacy continued to grow until the outbreak of war in 1941-1942. As a result of the military draft and accelerated programs, the enrollment dropped to a low of thirty one students in May 1944. During the war years, the College of Pharmacy participated in a Navy training program and in two research projects concerning synthetic and "sulfa" drugs.
The strengthening of community relations can be traced to Dr. Lewis' tenure. The "Annual Pharmacy Lectures" began in 1932. Thereafter, the college annually sponsored a day when pharmacists from throughout the state gathered to hear papers on a variety of pharmacy topics. With Lewis' support the lectures became an important link between the university and the statewide community. In 1937, the college began to broadcast pharmacy lectures of general interest over Ann Arbor and Detroit radio stations. The programs covered a diverse spectrum of subjects ranging from "Food and Drug Legislation" to "Chewing Gum." An extension course in pharmacy was offered for the first time in 1941, on a co-operative basis by the University of Michigan, the Michigan State Pharmacy Association, and the State Board of Control for Vocational Education. The course was conducted in Ann Arbor by a local retail pharmacist and enrolled 110 practicing pharmacists before the war interrupted the program.
Dean Lewis resigned in 1947 and was succeeded by Charles H. Stocking, a popular faculty member and secretary of the College of Pharmacy. A postwar resurgence of students saw enrollment double during the late 1940s. Demand for pharmacists far exceeded the supply and several additional faculty members were hired to meet the increased demands placed upon the college. Additional room for both students and faculty was provided for the college when an addition was completed to the Chemistry Building.
In 1951, Dean Stocking retired and was succeeded by Thomas D. Rowe, former dean of the Rutgers University College of Pharmacy. During Rowe's term (1951-1975) chemical and biochemical course work was strengthened and in 1960 the undergraduate program was lengthened to five years. In graduate work, a new Doctor of Pharmacy program was instituted to replace several masters-level programs. A significant site expansion of the college occurred in 1960 when the Pharmacy Research Building was completed. In addition, renovations in the C.C. Little Building provided the space for laboratories, classrooms, and offices necessary for the increased size and scope of the College.
Upon Dean Rowe's retirement in 1975, Ara G. Paul was named dean of the college. During the initial years of Paul's deanship extensive evaluation was undertaken in order to position the college for optimal growth through the end of the century. Among the significant curricular changes undertaken during the period 1975-1988 were:
The implementation of one integrated curriculum, to be taken by all students. (Previously, several curricula had been available.)
The termination of the B.S. Pharmacy degree in 1984.
The standardization of the internships program.
The introduction of an accelerated Ph.D. program for highly motivated students.
Ara Paul retired as dean in December 1995. He was succeeded by James W. Richards. Richards initially served as interim dean and was elected to a two-year term as dean on July 1, 1996. George L. Kenyon became dean in 1998 and served until 2004, when Frank Ascione was appointed to a five-year term. In 2009, Ascione was appointed to a second five-year term. One of the more notable developments during Ascione's tenure was the university's acquisition of the former Pfizer Research and Development facility (renamed North Campus Research Complex) in 2009, which enabled a variety of new research and educational opportunities for the college. The college hired many former Pfizer scientists to lead research programs.
For current academic program information see the College of Pharmacy website located at http://www.umich.edu/~pharmacy/.
Deans of the College of Pharmacy
1876-1905 Albert B. Prescott
1905-1917 Julius O. Schlotterbeck
1917-1919 Alviso B. Stevens
1919-1920 Henry Kraemer
1920-1933 Edward Krause
1933-1947 Howard B. Lewis
1947-1951 Charles H. Stocking
1951-1975 Thomas D. Rowe
1975-1995 Ara Paul
1995-1998 James W. Richards
1998-2004 George L. Kenyon
2004- Frank J. Ascione
The College of Pharmacy Publications (2.6 linear feet in four boxes) are divided into four series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, Topical Publications, and Student Publications. Some publications (or their successors) may no longer be available in print but are available on the school s website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan. Pharmacy Advancement Program.; University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.
Genre/Form:
Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Catalogs, College.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Posters.; Proceedings.; Programs.; Student publications.; University of Michigan. Pharmacy Advancement Program.; Drugs and pharmacy.; College of Pharmacy newsletter. Capsules.; Equilibrium. Hash sheet; Pharmacy newsletter. Pharmacy paper.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series includes bibliographies, brochures, bulletins or college catalogs, various histories of the college, and manuals such as Drugs and Pharmacy created in 1994, the Faculty Handbook published annually from 1981 to 1984, and Pharmacy Service in Smaller Hospitals: A Resource Handbook for Community Pharmacists and Administrators of Smaller Hospitals which was issued in 1958. This series also includes a run of the College of Pharmacy Newsletter produced from 1977 to 1982. There are also proceedings from the fiftieth (published in 1918), seventy-fifth (1952), and centennial (1976) anniversary celebrations of the College of Pharmacy. Also included in this series are scattered programs of the college convocation from 1951 to 1967 and 1985.
  - Bibliographies
    - Publications by the Staff of the University of Michigan College of Pharmacy, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General 1956-1993, undated (Box 1)
      (includes Pharmacy, Hospital and Clinical Pharmacy, and Medical Chemistry)
    - Drug and Pharmacy Experts, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Study in Pharmaceutical Fields, 1955-1971 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Study in Pharmacy, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Study in the Pharmaceutical Sciences, undated (Box 1)
    - Investing in Pharmacy's Future, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 1970-1983 (Box 1)
    - Opportunities for You in Pharmacy, undated (Box 1)
    - Pharmaceutics, undated (Box 1)
    - Post-Baccalaureate Doctor of Pharmacy Program, undated (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Doctor of Pharmacy Program, 1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - College Catalogs
      - 1880/1881-1981/1982, 49 folders (Box 1)
      - 1982/1983-2010/11, 13 folders (Box 2)
        (includes corrected 2004/05 issue)
  - Calendar for 125th Anniversary 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - Flyers 1989-1990, undated (Box 3)
  - Histories
    - History of the University of Michigan College of Pharmacy, 1971-1990 (Box 3)
    - A Revolution in Pharmaceutical Education, 1967 (Box 3)
    - The University of Michigan College of Pharmacy, 1876-1976 (Box 3)
  - Manuals
    - Drugs and Pharmacy, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Handbook 1981-1984, 1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Pharmacy Service in Smaller Hospitals: A Resource Handbook for Community Pharmacists and Administrators of Smaller Hospitals 1958 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - College of Pharmacy Newsletter
      - v.1-v.6 1977-1982, 6 folders (Box 3)
      - News 1993-1995, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - News Items, 1921-1922 (Box 3)
  - Posters
    - Graduate Programs 1953-1955 (Box 3)
  - Proceedings
    - Anniversary Celebrations
      - Centennial Celebration Proceedings, 1976 (Box 3)
      - The Fiftieth Anniversary Exercises, 1918 (Box 3)
      - 75th Anniversary Celebration, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Pharmacy, Medicine, Nursing Conference of Health Education, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Programs
    - Anniversary Celebrations
      - 75th Anniversary Celebration, 1951 (Box 3)
    - College of Pharmacy Annual Banquet, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Convocation
      - 1951 (Box 3)
      - 1967 (Box 3)
      - 1985 (Box 3)
    - Dedication of an Historical Marker, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Student Symposium 1984 (Box 3)
    - Senior Class Night 1978 (Box 3)
    - The Twentieth Annual Graduate Student Symposium 2000 (Box 3)
    - The Twenty-fifth Annual Graduate Student Meeting in Medicinal Chemistry 1992 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - Affirmative Action Report 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Honor Roll of Donors, 1996-1997, 1997 (Box 3)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series consists of materials produced by units within the College of Pharmacy. The Interdepartmental Program in Medicinal Chemistry produced calendars and flyers describing their seminar series. The Office of Educational Programs published brochures and pamphlets detailing the various continuing education seminars and lectures available. The Pharmacy Advancement Program has generated the newsletter Interactions from 1977 to the present. The four page InterUMactions was issued by this office from 1983 to 1985. Both publications were published for the alumni, but because of its size Interactions was able to focus more on the research activities of the faculty, students, and alumni of the College of Pharmacy.
  - Interdepartmental Program in Medicinal Chemistry Seminar Series
    - Calendars 1992 (Box 3)
    - Flyers 1989-1992, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Office of Educational Programs
    - Brochures
      - Independent Study Programs, 1986, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Seminars and Lectures 1983-1990 (Box 3)
  - Pharmacy Advancement Program
    - Brochures 1979-1984, undated (Box 3)
    - Newsletters
      - Interactions
        - 1977-1991, 14 folders (Box 3)
        - 1991-2003, 11 folders (Box 3)
      - InterUMactions, 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    - Programs
      - Prescott Circle Dinner, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Student Organizations
    - Report of Rho Chi Pharmacy Honor Society 1987 (Box 3)
  - Warner-Lambert Scientists Lecture Series
    - Programs 1991 (Box 3)
- Topical Publications
  The Topical Publications series includes alumni directories and the constitution and by-laws of the Association of the Pharmaceutical Alumni. These materials are found under the heading "alumni".
  - Alumni
    - Association of the Pharmaceutical Alumni
      - Constitution and By-Laws undated (Box 4)
    - Directories
      - Alumni Directory, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
      - Register of Alumni, 1869-1900 (Box 4)
        (see also Bulletins 1884/1885-1900/1901)
- Student Publications
  The Student Publications series contains newsletters published by students of the College of Pharmacy. These student newsletters include the titles Pharmacy Paper, issued from 1957 to 1959, Equilibrium, distributed from 1965 to 1969, and Pharmacy Newsletter in 1969. The Pharmacy Newsletter changed its title to The Hash Sheet, which continued publication from 1969 to 1980. In 1980 another new newsletter entitled Capsules was published. This title continued until 1983.
  - Newsletters
    - Capsuled News, circa 1965 (Box 4)
    - Capsules
      - 1980-1983, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Equilibrium, 1965-1967 (Box 4)
    - The Hash Sheet
      - 1969-1980, 11 folders (Box 4)
    - Pharmacy Newsletter
      - volume 1 1969 (Box 4)
    - Pharmacy Paper, 1957-1959 (Box 4)
- Archived College of Pharmacy Website
  This College of Pharmacy archived website documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the College of Pharmacy. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the College. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Website capture May 15, 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
    (Original URL http://www.umich.edu/~pharmacy)
  - Archived Website as of May 22, 2003, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 3)
  - Archived College of Pharmacy home page 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the College of Pharmacy 2010-[ongoing]